Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is דף יב, Daf
Yud-Bet, 12. It is what day is it in the עומר? Omer?
The 25th? 25th, right. The answer is עד יג, יג מידות. Ad
13, Yud-Gimmel Middot. Okay, it is 25th day of the עומר, Omer,
25th day of April. We pick up with the משנה Mishna on
יא עמוד ב. Yud-Alef Amud-Bet. Okay, and now we move, we've been
talking about the פסח Pesach and a חטאת Chatat if you do
it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is invalid and now we go, we
zoom in on the פסח. Pesach. הפסח ששחטו שחרית בארבעה עשר שלא
לשמו. HaPesach sheshchato shacharit bearba'asar shelo lishmo. If you שחט shcht it
on the 14th in the morning, the פסח Pesach is only the
זמן zman is בין הערביים bein arbaim from חצות chatzot onward, 12:30
onward. So, and that's when you do it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
it's invalid, and according to a certain other opinion when you do
others לשם פסח l'shem Pesach it's invalid during that, that's one opinion.
Anyway, during that time of זמנו, zmano, which is 12:30 onward, בין
הערביים. bein arbaim. But let's say you שחט shcht it in the
morning שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. Now, if you שחט shcht a פסח
Pesach when it's אינו זמנו, eino zmano, not its time and שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo it's כשר, kosher, it's a שלמים. shlamim. Okay, so
the question is, is the morning אינו זמנו, eino zmano, not its
time and שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it's כשר kosher as a שלמים,
shlamim, or is it considered זמנו zmano and שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
is פסול? pasul? Let's say you did it, let's not the let's
say. Let's see what it is. If it's לשמו lishmo then it's
clearly invalid because it's a פסח שלא בזמנו. Pesach shelo bizmano.
So that's invalid, okay, a פסח Pesach on the 14th before the
זמן zman is invalid. But now you שחט shcht it שלא לשמו.
shelo lishmo. רבי יהושע מכשיר, Rabbi Yehoshua machshir, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
says it's כשר, kosher, כאילו נשחט בשלושה עשר, ke'ilu nishchat bishlosha-asar, like
you שחט shcht it on the 13th, this is שלא בזמנו shelo
bizmano and therefore it's like a פסח שלא בזמנו, Pesach shelo bizmano,
שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it's a שלמים, shlamim, it's כשר. kosher. בן
בתירא פוסל כאילו נשחט בין הערביים. Ben Betayra posel ke'ilu nishchat bein
arbaim.
בן בתירא Ben Betayra says no, it's as if it's בזמנו bizmano
because the afternoon is coming, and therefore since it's a פסח Pesach
that's considered enough sometime during this day is זמנו, zmano, שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo would be invalid. And as Michael's question pointed out, therefore
on the 14th in the morning, whether according to this, whether it's
לשמו lishmo or שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it's invalid. לשמו lishmo it's
invalid because it's a פסח קודם זמנו, Pesach kodem zmano, and שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo it's invalid because it is considered enough
זמנו zmano that you're שחט shchting a פסח, Pesach, you know, לשם
אחרים l'shem acherim and therefore בזמנו bizmano that's invalid. Okay, so that's
what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says. I mean that's what בן בתירא
Ben Betayra says. Now, we have really something which is really like
a completely separate משנה mishna here. So imagine that there's a two
big dots, this is a different point. אמר שמעון בן עזאי, Amar
Shimon ben Azzai, שמעון בן עזאי Shimon ben Azzai said, מקובל אני
מפי שבעים ושנים זקנים, mekubal ani mipi shivim u-shnayim zekenim, I have
a tradition from 72 elders. I don't know why 72, it should
be 71, right, that's the standard סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Maybe there's 71 and
then there's like the נשיא Nasi or something. Anyway, ביום שהושיבו את
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה בישיבה, beyom she-hoshivu et Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah
bayeshiva, on the day that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar was sort of
like made the head. Right, that was a whole big event, right,
yes, שכל הזבחים
הנאכלים שנזבחו שלא לשמם כשרים, she-kol hazvachim hane'echalim she-nizbachu shelo lishmaman k'sherim,
any of the edible sacrifices that were שחט shcht שלא לשמו shelo
lishmo are כשר, kosher, אלא שלא עלו לבעלים לשום חובה, ella she-lo
alu laba'alim lishum hovah, but they the בעלים ba'alim don't fulfill their
obligation, חוץ מן הפסח ומן החטאת, chutz min hapesach u-min hachatat, with
the exception of פסח Pesach and חטאת. Chatat. Now that sounds like
exactly everything we've seen, that anything שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is כשר
kosher but the בעלים ba'alim don't get credit, except for פסח Pesach
and חטאת. Chatat. He just added one little word. הנאכלים. Hane'echalim. This
is true about the edible sacrifices. What is the only sacrifice that
is not edible? An עולה, olah, or חטאת פנימיות, chatat pnimiyot, but
we already said חוץ מן החטאת. chutz min hachatat. So the גמרא,
Gemara, so the משנה mishna concludes and says, ולא הוסיף בן עזאי,
v'lo hosif Ben Azzai, by saying this, בן עזאי Ben Azzai what
the only thing he added to the list that we had said
before, אלא העולה. ella ha-olah. Implicit in בן עזאי Ben Azzai's tradition
was that an עולה olah שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is also פסול,
pasul, ולא הודו לו חכמים, v'lo hodu lo chachamim, but the חכמים
chachamim did not agree to adding עולה olah to the list, the
list is limited to חטאת chatat and פסח. pesach. Okay, so that's
really a separate point about does the list include anything beyond חטאת
chatat and פסח. pesach. But the first point is what is the
story about פסח Pesach the morning of the 14th? Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, said
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, אמר רבי אושעיא, amar Rabbi Oshaya, מכשיר היה
בן בתירא בפסח ששחטו שחרית בארבעה עשר לשמו. Machshir hayah Ben Betayra
b'Pesach sheshchato shacharit bearba'asar lishmo.
When בן בתירא Ben Betayra says that the morning of the 14th
is enough בזמנו bizmano that when it's שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo it's invalid, what he's really saying is not it's enough
בזמנו bizmano because by this afternoon it'll be זמן. zman. What he's
really saying is if you really ask me, says בן בתירא, Ben
Betayra, if you really ask me to be honest, I would tell
you that if you שחט shcht it a פסח Pesach in the
morning לשם פסח l'shem Pesach it's כשר. kosher. That the זמן zman
of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach really belongs in the morning. And
since it
could really be brought already first thing in the morning, therefore when
you do it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it's פסול pasul in the
morning. Okay, it's not because the time is coming up in the
afternoon. It's because it really is the time and that's why שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo is invalid.
Wait, I'm sorry. So לשמו lishmo is valid for בן בתירא? Ben
Betayra? Yeah, and לשמו lishmo according to the תנא קמא... Tanna Kamma...
Is not.
We have, okay, so מודה בן בתירה בפסח—that’s modeh Ben Beteira bePesach
what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
Okay, but ארבעת שלא לשמה, arba'at shelo lishmah, דכולי יומא זמניה הוא,
dekulei yoma zemaneih hu, he really פוסקן poskens that the זמן zman
begins in the morning.
So as Michael says, really they’re having a more fundamental debate: can
you bring a קרבן פסח korban Pesach first thing in the morning?
This other debate is really just a derivative of that debate, which
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. ומה כאילו, u'mai
ke'ilu, so what does he mean when he says if you שחט
shechted it in the morning it’s like you שחט shechted it in
the afternoon, which makes it sound like it’s enough בזמנו bizmano because
the afternoon is coming? He really should have said it is the
זמן. zman. So אדידי, adidi, אמר רבי יהושע, amar Rabbi Yehoshua, כאילו,
ke'ilu, since רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said it’s like you שחט shechted
it yesterday, it’s so שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano, it’s like you שחט
shechted it yesterday, אמר איהו נמי כאילו, amar ihu nami ke'ilu, he
says no, it’s like you שחט shechted it in the afternoon, working
with your structure. But if really, bottom line, I really believe it’s
not like it’s the afternoon; it’s the morning is just as good.
So אי הכי, ei hachi, if that’s true, we’ll get to all
that, אי דמפלגי בשלא לשמה ליפלגי בלשמה, ei demapligi be'shelo lishmah liflagi
be'lishmah, why argue about the שלא לשמה shelo lishmah which is a
derivative debate? Argue about the more fundamental question: is a פסח כשר
Pesach kasher first thing in the morning? So the גמרא Gemara says
yeah, you’re right, it could have. אי פליגו בלשמה, ei paligu be'lishmah,
had they debated the question about a קרבן פסח korban Pesach first
thing in the morning לשמה, lishmah, הוה אמינא hava amina I would
have said fine, they argue whether it’s כשר kasher first thing in
the morning, אבל בשלא לשמה מודה רבי יהושע לבן בתירה, aval be'shelo
lishmah modeh Rabbi Yehoshua leBen Beteira, fine, they argue whether it’s כשר
kasher first thing in the morning, but when it’s שלא לשמה shelo
lishmah I would think that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would agree that
שלא לשמה shelo lishmah in the morning is פסול pasul because he
would agree since the זמן zman is coming in the afternoon, it’s
enough בזמנו bizmano to פסול pasul when it’s שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah.
Okay. הוה אמינא מודה רבי יהושע לבן בתירה, hava amina modeh Rabbi
Yehoshua leBen Beteira, הואיל ומקצת ראוי, ho'il u'miktzat ra'uy,
since some of the day is going to be זמן, zman, so
had they argued whether it’s כשר kasher in the morning, I would
have said even if you think it’s not כשר kasher in the
morning, you might think that it’s פסול שלא לשמה. pasul shelo lishmah.
קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so therefore they wanted to have
their debate about to tell you that about the שלא לשמה shelo
lishmah scenario that בן בתירה Ben Beteira holds שלא לשמה shelo lishmah
is פסול pasul because he really holds it’s כשר kasher first thing,
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is כשר
kasher because he holds two things: A, it’s not כשר kasher first
thing in the morning, you can't bring קרבן פסח korban Pesach first
thing in the morning, and B, even though the זמן zman is
coming up in the afternoon, it’s still not enough בזמנו bizmano to
say that it’s פסול pasul when you do it שלא לשמה. shelo
lishmah. Okay. So bottom line is that the גמרא Gemara is going
to reject this obviously, this is an extreme interpretation that somebody would
say קרבן פסח korban Pesach is כשר kasher first thing in the
morning. But that’s how the גמרא Gemara is interpreting the debate. Right
here, let me try to, maybe I’ll try to demonstrate, okay?
Rabbi Ben Yehuda's Ben Yehoshua, right?
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and בן בתירה. Ben Beteira. Right, okay. If
I did I say it wrong? Fine, okay, whatever. Okay, anyway, here’s
noon, okay, here’s sunrise, whatever, fine, here’s sunset. So, okay,
so what the גמרא Gemara is basically saying is that בן בתירה
Ben Beteira says, right, בן בתירה Ben Beteira says that the פסח
Pesach is כשר kasher all during this entire time and
אלו ואלו באים לשם חובה. eilu ve'eilu ba'im l'shem chovah.
And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no, the פסח Pesach is only
כשר kasher here, right, when it’s לשמה. lishmah. Okay, and so we’re
debating though when you did it, right, over here, שלא לשמה. shelo
lishmah.
So what we’re saying is that בן בתירה Ben Beteira is saying
שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is פסול pasul because this is בזמנו, bizmano,
so פסח בזמנו שלא לשמה Pesach bizmano shelo lishmah is פסול. pasul.
And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is saying שלא לשמה shelo lishmah done
over here is כשר kasher because it’s שלא לשמה שלא בזמנו. shelo
lishmah shelo bizmano. Okay, but the reason, but it’s really a derivative
of when do you think the פסח Pesach is כשר? kasher? And
the גמרא Gemara says why didn’t you just debate when the פסח
Pesach was כשר? kasher? Because if you had just debated when the
פסח Pesach was כשר, kasher, I might have said that okay, רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says it’s only כשר kasher here, but he would
agree that שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is פסול pasul because it’s considered
enough בזמנו bizmano because the זמן zman is coming. So it wanted
to tell you that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua holds two things: number
one, the פסח Pesach itself is only כשר kasher here, and number
two, even though the זמן zman is coming up later in the
day, שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is כשר kasher over here because it
still is שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano, and שלא לשמה shelo lishmah by
a פסח Pesach when it’s not the זמן פסח zman Pesach is
כשר. kasher. Okay, so that’s what the גמרא Gemara says, but their
core debate is this. All right, so let’s take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says really? So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
והכתיב, ve'haktiv, so you really mean to tell me that somebody thinks
a פסח Pesach can be כשר kasher first thing? והכתיב ve'haktiv doesn’t
it say בין הערבים, bein ha'arbayim, between the eves, which is generally
understood to be the first evening is when the sun moves like
to the afternoon, like it’s a little bit after noon after, you
know, because now it’s the evening in the sense the sun is
heading towards the מערב, ma'arav, right, the ערב, erev, it’s heading towards
the west, and then the second evening is when the sun actually
sets? So between the evenings is the afternoon, the evening number one,
the
PM. between those two points, that's בין הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. Yes.
I thought it was twilight.
Yeah, twilight. Two lights.
Okay, but twilight is not the halachic definition of בין הערבים. bein
ha'arbayim. That would be, that's more like, that's more like בין השמשות,
bein hashmashos, which is also two lights, between the suns or whatever.
I don't know, I can't, I don't know the exact mapping onto
the English terms. But anyway, בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim halachically is the
afternoon. Okay, so אמרו ליה בריה דרבי אילאי בין שני ארבעים ערבים.
amru leh breh d'rabi ilai bein shnei arba'im arvayim. It's between the
two evenings of, not the, not these two evenings, but these two
evenings. Why? Sunrise is the end of the previous night. So between
the ערב erev of the previous day and the ערב erev of
the sunset here, that's the בין הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. So it means
the whole day. בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim means the whole day. So
the גמרא gemara says, really? Now we're supposed to read בין הערבים
bein ha'arbayim in the תורה Torah meaning the whole day? So, תמיד
דכתיב ביה, tamid d'chasiv bei, so you mean to tell me the
קרבן תמיד korban tamid where it says בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim הכי
נמי דכולי יומא כשר הוא? hachi nami d'chulo yoma kashar hu? You
could bring the תמיד tamid at any time during the day, the
afternoon תמיד? tamid? התם מדכתיב את הכבש אחד תעשה בבקר. hasam mi-d'chasiv
es hakeves echad sa'aseh baboker. No, since it says one in the
morning and the other
בין הערבים, bein ha'arbayim, מכלל דבין הערבים בין הערבים ממש. m'khlal d'bein
ha'arbayim bein ha'arbayim mamash. That בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim means the standard
בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim meaning, which is the afternoon. Okay, not this
extended meaning. So the גמרא gemara says why? If בין הערבים bein
ha'arbayim can mean the whole day, I could still read the פסוק.
pasuk. אימא חד בבקר ואידך כולי יומא. ema chad baboker ve'idach kulo
yoma. The first one has to be in the morning,
and one could be anytime in the day. What's pushing me to
say it? That בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim I should read it more
narrowly if בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim can mean the whole day? No,
because it says אחד בבקר ולא שנים בבקר, echad baboker velo shnayim
baboker, one in the morning, and not two. So from that I
learn to read that בין הערבים bein ha'arbayim as a narrow בין
הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. נרות, neros, says the גמרא, gemara, if that's true,
how about lighting the נרות neros of the מנורה? menorah? דכתיב בין
הערבים, d'chasiv bein ha'arbayim, light it between the eves. הכי נמי דכולי
יומא כשר? hachi nami d'chulo yoma kashar? You mean to tell me
I can light the מנורה menorah anytime during the day? No, שאני
התם דכתיב מערב עד בקר, shani hasam d'chasiv me-erev ad boker, from
the evening to the morning. So therefore you understand that that ארבעים
arbayim means afternoon-evening time, does not mean the whole day. ותניא, v'sanya,
and by the way, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, מערב עד
בקר תן לה מידתה שתהא דולקת והולכת מערב עד בקר. me-erev ad
boker tein lah midasah shetehei dolekes v'holeches me-erev ad boker. This really
גמרא gemara could did not have to quote this. Anyway, it has
to have enough oil that it can burn throughout the night. דבר
אחר אין לך עבודה שכשרה מערב עד בקר אלא זו בלבד. davar
acher ein lekha avodah she'kesherah me-erev ad boker ela zo bilvad. This
is the only עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש beis hamikdash that
begins during the day and continues, like, you know, and can take
place like throughout the night. Okay, anyway, that's really a parenthetical statement.
Now, קטרת דכתיב בה בין הערבים. ketores d'chasiv bah bein ha'arbayim. How
about the incense? הכי נמי דכולי יומא כשר? hachi nami d'chulo yoma
kashar? Do you mean to tell me that you can burn the
קטרת ketores anytime during the day? No, שאני נרות קטרת דאיתקש לנרות.
shani neros ketores d'itkeshu l'neros. No, because there it says ובהעלת אהרן
את הנרת בין הערבים יקטירנה. uv'haalos aharon es haneros bein ha'arbayim yaktirenah.
It says explicitly light it when אהרן Aharon is doing the lighting
of the מנורה. menorah. So since we've proven that the lighting of
the מנורה menorah because מערב עד בקר me-erev ad boker literally means
afternoon, here too by the קטרת. ketores.
So basically you made a, you know, דקדוק לשון dikduk lashon only
for one case?
Exactly, exactly. This term means the whole day except we're going to
in all other times we're going to make it mean the afternoon.
Okay, so the גמרא gemara says,
דאיתקש לנרא, d'itkeshu l'nera, התם נמי כתיב שם תזבח את הפסח בערב.
hasam nami chasiv sham tizbach es hapesach ba'erev. If you're going to
say ערב erev tells you it means literally afternoon, it says by
the קרבן פסח korban pesach also ערב. erev. So the גמרא gemara
says no, ההוא לאיחור דבר הוא דאתא. hahu l'ichar davar hu d'asa.
No, that means to tell me that when it's brought in the
afternoon, it has to be the last thing brought, even after the
תמיד. tamid. It has to be brought after the תמיד. tamid. דתניא,
d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, יאחר דבר שנאמר בו בערב
בין הערבים. ye'achar davar shene'emar bo ba'erev bein ha'arbayim. קרבן פסח korban
pesach that has two statements about evening, ערב erev and בין הערבים,
bein ha'arbayim, that comes later than לדבר שלא נאמר בו אלא בין
הערבים בלבד. l'davar shelo ne'emar bo ela bein ha'arbayim bilvad. To the
תמיד, tamid, the תמיד tamid only says בין הערבים. bein ha'arbayim. So
the הלכה halacha is they would bring the קרבן פסח korban pesach
after the afternoon תמיד. tamid. So now the גמרא gemara says, wait,
let me get this straight. You could bring it in the morning,
but if you bring it in the afternoon, it has to be
the last thing in the afternoon. What? So the גמרא gemara says
ומי איכא מידי דאילו שחט ליה מצפרא, u'mi ka midi d'ilu shachit
lei mi-tzifra, if you had shechted it in the morning, אמרת זמניה
הוא, amarta zimnei hu, it's the זמן zman and you could do
it anytime in the morning. וכי מטי לבין הערבים אמרת יאחר דבר?
vechi mati l'bein ha'arbayim amarta ye'achar davar? But now that it becomes
the afternoon,
it has to be the last thing you bring in the afternoon?
So the גמרא gemara says אין, in, yes, דאמר רבי יוחנן. d'amar
rabbi yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says הלכה מתפלל של מנחה ואחר
כך מתפלל של מוספין. halacha mispallel shel mincha v'achar kakh mispallel shel
musafim. That if you forgot to דאוון daven
מוסף, musaf, happened sometimes, like it's ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you're in
a rush, whatever, you didn't דאוון daven מוסף, musaf, you say to
דאוון daven it later, then you wake up in the afternoon and
מנחה mincha says oh my god I didn't get around to דאוון
daven מוסף. musaf. So you
realize it's ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, that's always the interesting case. I'm
going to get back to that. Like I, I, I like to
tell students when would be a case where you would דאוון daven
the following three דאוונינג davening in a row: מנחה, mincha, שחרית, shacharis,
מוסף? musaf? And in this order: מנחה, mincha, שחרית, shacharis, מוסף. musaf.
And the answer is you didn't realize that it was ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh in the morning. Okay, now it's already the afternoon. So
the first thing you have to דאוון daven is מנחה, mincha, then
you do a תשלומין tashlumin for שחרית, shacharis, and then you דאוון
daven מוסף. musaf. So you דאוון daven מנחה, mincha, שחרית, shacharis, מוסף.
musaf. Anyway, but let's say you... דאוון daven שחרית Shachris but you
skipped מוסף, Musaf, and now it's the afternoon. So you should normally
say well, it's מוסף Musaf and then מנחה. Mincha. No. Since it's
the afternoon and it's the זמן zman of מנחה, Mincha, תדיר ושאינו
תדיר תדיר קודם. tadir v'she'eino tadir tadir kodem. So first you דאוון
daven מנחה, Mincha, and then you דאוון daven מוסף. Musaf. מוסף Musaf
isn't תשלומין, tashlumim, it's still the זמן zman of מוסף Musaf in
the afternoon. But because the because מנחה Mincha is תדיר, tadir, it's
first מנחה Mincha and then מוסף. Musaf. Okay, אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan. So even though normally מוסף Musaf in the morning comes
first, מוסף Musaf in the afternoon comes last. Okay, or not comes
first, comes before מנחה. Mincha. One minute, אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, הלכה מתפלל של מנחה ואחר כך מתפלל של מוספין. Halacha mispallel
shel mincha ve'achar kach mispallel shel musafim.
So therefore here too, if it's in the morning, it comes anytime
in the morning, but if you got it to the afternoon, it's
gonna come after the תמיד. tamid. So we can live with that.
Yes.
So the prayer and sacrifice co-existed.
Yes. Well, being paralleled, what?
No, the comparison is interesting.
Yeah, because prayer כנגד קרבן תמידים. keneged korban tamidim.
No, that's not clear. I mean I know the גמרא Gemara gives
the impression at some places although I don't think it ever says
it explicitly, that the prayer was established after the קרבנות korbanot in
order to replace the קרבנות, korbanot, but even when the גמרא Gemara
says כנגד קרבנות, keneged korbanot, it's not saying that it did not
that it was only established after there was no longer בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Most people did not make it to the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash most of their life, you know, certainly most of the
year. So the idea it could very well be that the תפילה
tefillah
existed, exactly, they had שוהלס shuls before and so on. Anyway, but
certainly the גמרא Gemara is drawing these nice comparisons. Okay, anyway the
גמרא Gemara says like this, והכתיב, v'hakativ, okay, ובין הערבים. u'vein ha'arbayim.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, ובין הערבים דכתיב גבי קטורת
ונרות למה לי? u'vein ha'arbayim d'chtiv gabei ketoret v'nerot lamah li? One
minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, but if that's true that
that that ובין הערבים u'vein ha'arbayim means the whole day, and then
by קטורת ketoret and the נרות, nerot, it's only limited to mean
evening because it says בערב ba'erev or whatever, so why did it
even say ובין הערבים u'vein ha'arbayim if it has no halachic no
meaning? Right? It says the day only to limit it to the
afternoon. ועוד, Ve'od, and not only that, השיב רבי, heishiv Rabbi, he's
a ברייתא, baraita, תוספתא, tosefta, השיב רבי תחת בן בתירא לדברי רבי
יהושע. heishiv Rabbi Tachas Ben Betheira l'divrei Rabbi Yehoshua. Rabbi comes in
the place, I love the phrase, like coming I'm gonna like pinch
hit for you. Rabbi stands in for בן בתירא Ben Betheira and
challenges רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua in the following way. And here's how
he challenges רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, who says that the פסח pesach
morning of the 13th is כשר. kosher. Morning of the 14th is
כשר. kosher. He says לא, lo, no, אם אמרת בשלושה עשר, im
amarta bishloshah asar, it's כשר kosher שלא לשמו, she'lo lishmo, שאין מקצתו
ראוי, she'ein miktzaso ra'ui, because on the 13th no part of the
13th could be you could bring a קרבן פסח. korban pesach. So
תאמר בארבעה עשר, tomar b'arba'ah asar, are you gonna say it's כשר
kosher שלא לשמו she'lo lishmo the morning of the 14th because you're
gonna say it's not the זמן, zman, it's not the time? שמקצתו
ראוי, she'miktzaso ra'ui, part of the 14th is the זמן. zman. So
it's זמנו, zmano, so it's still שלא לשמו she'lo lishmo should be
פסול. pasul. Now that's not בן בתירא Ben Betheira himself talking, that's
Rabbi talking on behalf of בן בתירא, Ben Betheira, but he makes
it very clear that he's saying this: you can't do it here,
but since it since later in the day it's זמנו, zmano, it's
already enough זמנו zmano to be invalid. So when it's שלא לשמו.
she'lo lishmo. אלא Ela says the גמרא Gemara fine, reject that read,
reject the read that they are arguing when is a פסח pesach
itself כשר. kosher. אלא אמר רבי יוחנן פוסל היה בן בתירא בפסח
ששחטו בארבעה עשר שחרית בין לשמו בין שלא לשמו. Ela amar Rabbi
Yochanan, posel hayah Ben Betheira b'pesach she'shachato b'arba'ah asar shachris bein lishmo
bein she'lo lishmo. You're right.
Everybody agrees that the פסח pesach is only כשר kosher over here,
okay, everybody agrees that, okay, and here בן בתירא Ben Betheira says
if it's שלא לשמו, she'lo lishmo, בן בתירא Ben Betheira says it's
פסול pasul and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says it's כשר. kosher. Why
does בן בתירא Ben Betheira say it's פסול? pasul? Because it's enough
בזמנו, bizmano, because the זמן zman is coming later and therefore it's
פסח pesach that is בזמנו bizmano sometime today שלא לשמו she'lo lishmo
is פסול, pasul, which is what our first משנה Mishna teaches, a
פסח בזמנו שלא לשמו pesach bizmano she'lo lishmo is פסול. pasul. Because
the time is coming later.
It's not later, it's coming today. Halachically, like we're gonna see in
a minute, you know, there's not a real like halachic distinction between
normally we work in day units, okay? So, you know, so therefore
it's enough בזמנו bizmano we don't break it down into like let's
say it was one minute before before ובין הערבים, u'vein ha'arbayim, right?
So you could say na-uh, one minute is one minute, there's a
line, you haven't crossed the line yet. So that's their debate. But
what רבי בן בתירא Rabbi Ben Betheira saying is the halachic unit
of זמן, zman, we we measure in days. And since today is
זמנו, zmano, it's considered פסח בזמנו. pesach bizmano.
And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would say לשמו, lishmo, that if you
שחט׳ד shachted it בארבעה עשר... b'arba'ah asar...
Everybody everybody agrees that לשמו lishmo it's פסול. pasul. It's לשמו lishmo
before it's the real זמן zman and therefore it's פסול. pasul. Okay.
So now the גמרא's Gemara gonna say like this: פוסל היה בן
בתירא בפסח ששחטו בארבעה עשר שחרית בין לשמו בין שלא לשמו הוא
מקצתו ראוי. posel hayah Ben Betheira b'pesach she'shachato b'arba'ah asar shachris bein
lishmo bein she'lo lishmo, ho miktzaso ra'ui. Since it's partly it's right,
so לשמו lishmo is פסול pasul because it's a פסח לשמו pesach
lishmo before it's the real time, and שלא לשמו she'lo lishmo is
פסול pasul because it's the time is coming up later today and
that's enough to פסול pasul it שלא לשמו. she'lo lishmo. So the
גמרא Gemara says מגדיף בה רבי אבהו, migadef bei Rabbi Abahu, רבי
אבהו Rabbi Abahu like mocked this, scoffed at it, I should say
that's a good word for מגדיף, migadef, scoffed. אם כן, Im kein,
he said, literally it means a curse. אם כן Im kein פסח
כשר pesach kasher לבן בתירא היכי משכחת לה? l'Ben Betheira heichi mishkachas
lah? How you ever gonna get a כשר kosher פסח pesach לבן
בתירא? l'Ben Betheira? Why? This time he says says is not kosher
for the פסח Pesach בין לשמו בין שלא לשמו. bein lishmo bein
shelo lishmo. לשמו Lishmo it's not kosher because it's a פסח Pesach
before the time. שלא לשמו Shelo lishmo it's פסול passul because the
time is coming up. So this period is like a blackout day,
you know, for פסח. Pesach. No פסח Pesach can be kosher in
any way בין לשמו בין שלא לשמו bein lishmo bein shelo lishmo
here. So he says, if that's true, any time a קורבן פסח
korban Pesach that you let's say you sanctified it back here and
it's going to now pass into this period is now passing into
a time that is a complete time that is a blackout for
קורבן פסח. korban Pesach. So that should be considered דחוי. dichoy. It's
a time when the קורבן korban in no way could be brought
and that should be like the קורבן korban should be seen as
pushed off, pushed away. And then it should remain invalid. That's his
argument. Let's take a look. I know, he says, היכי משכחת לה.
heichi mashkachas la. האי דאפרשיה בצפרא, ha de-afrishei ba-tzafra,
if you separated it the morning of the 14th, דחוי מעיקרא הוא.
dachui mei-ikara hu. It was never fit to be a קורבן פסח.
korban Pesach. You sanctified it at a time when it could not
be brought at all. It couldn't be brought לשמו lishmo and it
couldn't be brought שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. So that's considered like it
was not valid at the time you sanctified it so the sanctity
should be דחוי dachui which is sort of like pushed off, which
would be like, you know, it should be like stigmatized. Okay? It,
you know, there's a blot on the on the it doesn't get
rid of it. והאי דאפרשינהו מאתמול, ve-ha de-afrishinhu me-etmol,
if you separated it on the 13th, you sanctified it, נראה ונדחה.
nira ve-nidcha. That's even worse. Something that was once fit and then
was pushed away is considered even more rejection, okay? And therefore, you
know, it's like if you didn't get hired for a job you
could reapply. If you got hired and then you got fired, don't
try coming back. So anyway, נראה ונדחה nira ve-nidcha is always worse.
So he says this period he thinks since in no way can
the קורבן korban be kosher, right? Think what other קורבן, korban, you
know, any other קורבן korban could be kosher at any other time.
An עולה, olah, חטאת, chatas, or שלמים shelamim you could bring it
at any time. Okay. Now I guess you could sort of say
what if it's like one of the one of like a something
that's sanctified for the רגל, regal, like the שלמי ציבור shalmei tzibbur
that you sanctified? That's an interesting question. But anyway, he says, but
here, normally a פסח Pesach is either kosher לשמו lishmo or it's
kosher שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. But here's a time it's not kosher
for anything and that passing through that time should push it away
and should invalidate it. So there's a lot of things you could
respond to that. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אלא אמר
רבי אבהו, ella amar Rabbi Abbahu, תהא לאחר חצות. tehei l-achar chatzos.
So רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu decided the only way you could sanctify
a קורבן פסח korban Pesach according to בן בתירה Ben Beteira was
you sanctified it already in the afternoon. Okay? Don't sanctify it before,
don't sanctify it on in the morning. That'll sort of invalidate it
because it's passing through this blackout time. You can only sanctify it
once it's already the afternoon and ready to be brought. So the
גמרא Gemara has better answers. That was that was that was רבי
אבהו's Rabbi Abbahu answer.
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, אפילו תימא מצפרא. afilu teima mi-tzafra. No, you
can sanctify it in the morning. אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום, ein
mechusar zman l-bo bayom, which is a variation of what of בן
בתירה's Ben Beteira whole position is. It's sort of what I said
a minute ago to Dave. We measure time in whole days. We
don't measure them in part days. So therefore he says, when you
sanctify it here, you don't say oh look, the קורבן פסח korban
Pesach is existing in now a time when it can't be brought.
Since it can be brought later today, it's living in a time
when it can be brought. Later today it can be brought. We
measure in whole days. The same reason that בן בתירה Ben Beteira
says if you שחט shacht it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it's פסול
passul because its time is later today, he is saying, okay, so
we say that today is its time and therefore even when it
passes through the morning, it's not in a time that it can't
be brought. This minute it can't be brought but the time measured
in units of days is it can be brought today and therefore
it's not נדחה, nidche, it's not pushed off. Okay? רב פפא אמר,
Rav Papa amar, אפילו תימא מאורתא. afilu teima mei-ortsa. You could even
sanctify it the night before. Why could you sanctify it the night
before? לילה אין מחוסר זמן. layla ein mechusar zman. If something can
be brought in the morning but can't be brought in the night,
okay, again we just look at it as like we don't measure
it at this minute. We say night and day are the same
time are the same unit and therefore so even if you sanctify
it like the night before you could say now there's two reasons
it can't be brought. You don't bring קורבנות korbanos at night
and you can't bring it until tomorrow afternoon.
But the גמרא Gemara says no,
halachically night morning afternoon are the same day and therefore even if
you're sancti- even at nighttime from the night before we say it's
already the time of the פסח. Pesach. Why is it the time
of the פסח? Pesach? Because it can be brought in the same
halachic day, we're in the 14th later in the day in the
afternoon and therefore it's not נדחה, nidche, it's not pushed off. By
the way, here's a great example of that. I was waiting for
somebody to say, if we're so afraid that there's this blackout time
and it should be considered נדחה, nidche, why can I ever sanctify
an- a sacrifice at night? You can't bring קורבנות korbanos at night.
So if I sanctify my עולה olah why don't we say oh
it's נדחה, nidche, you can't bring it right now, right? You know?
So no, it's because I can bring it in the morning. We
don't measure by this minute. So we say we don't measure by
this minute. You'll be able to bring it later today. It's not
נדחה. nidche. So that's what it's sounding like, that is but once
but I but I but once but it's not about sanctifying. Once
you say that this is considered to be זמנו, zmano, then when
you sanctify it over here, and then you come into the 14th,
you're in זמנו. zmano. You're not in a לאו בזמנו lo bizmano
period. But you're right, it's funny the way it phrases it. Yeah,
it's working it out. But the basic upshot is, is that the
14th is considered זמנו, zmano, because you can bring it later in
the day. We measure things in whole units. Okay. So, okay. Where
was it? So, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now this idea
אין מחוסר זמן לבו ביום ein mechusar zman livo beyom or night
is not לילה אין מחוסר זמן. laila ein mechusar zman. It's not
considered lacking in time for the night. דתני, detani, now this phrase
of מחוסר זמן mechusar zman actually has a more technical meaning. It
just doesn't just mean you can do it later today. מחוסר זמן
mechusar zman specifically has to do with a קרבן korban whose time
has not yet reached. For example, it's not yet the eighth day.
Right? A קרבן korban is only כשר kasher when it's eight days
old. So here's going to be the original meaning of this term
of מחוסר זמן mechusar zman later today or מחוסר זמן mechusar zman
the night before is comes from the following point. Let's read it.
דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל. detani d'bei Rabbi Yishmael. ליל שמיני, leil shemini,
let's say you have an animal that is, that is, it was
born, you know, seven days ago. It's eighth day birthday, whatever. It's
going to be eight days old, I don't know, Monday morning. Okay,
so now Sunday night, it's not yet eight days old. It'll only
be eight days old Monday morning. Okay, or whatever.
So, or it won't be able to be brought as a קרבן
korban till Monday morning. ליל שמיני נכנס לדיר להתעשר. leil shemini nichnas
ledir lehit'aser. Okay, so when you do מעשר בהמה, maaser behema, you
take all your animals that were born this year or since the
last מעשר בהמה, maaser behema, you put them into a pen, you
walk them through a gate, you count one, two, three and the
tenth one you hit with a stick or with like a red
dye and whatever, and then you mark it and that's going to
be the מעשר בהמה. maaser behema. But you only do that with
animals once they're eight days old, because then when you hit it
and you sanctify it, it's fit to be brought as a קרבן.
korban. It's eight days old. Can I do it at night and
include in the group of animals I'm counting for מעשר בהמה maaser
behema an animal that's a little baby sheep that's only that, you
know, was born just whatever, seven days ago and its eighth, you
know, eighth day is tomorrow morning. Okay, or I mean it might,
you know, and so because, and the answer is so I can't
bring it till tomorrow and it's not yet even, it's never yet
been fit to be brought as a קרבן, korban, okay, because it's
because a קרבן korban has to be brought in the morning and
its eighth day is tomorrow. Okay, and the הלכה halacha is yes,
you can do this the night before, Sunday night, because since in
the morning it'll be fit to be brought as a קרבן, korban,
it's already considered to be fit to be brought as a
קרבן. korban. You got it? Okay, and that's the idea of מחוסר
זמן. mechusar zman. מחוסר זמן mechusar zman is it's not yet full
eight days, okay, but it really, but the point is, but it'll
be eight days in the morning. All right. So, לילה אין מחוסר
זמן דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל ליל שמיני נכנס לדיר להתעשר. laila ein
mechusar zman detani d'bei Rabbi Yishmael leil shemini nichnas ledir lehit'aser.
I mean really the night is the eighth day because we count
in whole day units. But it's not yet fit to be brought
because it's not the morning. And nevertheless,
even though it's not the morning, since it is its eighth day,
or at least the nighttime of its eighth day, that's considered already
fit to be brought as a קרבן. korban. ורבי אפטוריקי. verabbi aptoriki.
דרבי אפטוריקי רמי. derabbi aptoriki rami.
He showed a contradiction. כתיב ksiv one verse says והיה שבעת ימים
תחת אמו. vehaya shivas yamim tachas imo. The animal has to be
seven days with its mother. So seven days, so this is what's
as soon as seven days are over, it is the night of
the eighth. הלילה חזי. halaila chazi.
By the night of the eighth, it's fit to be brought as
a קרבן. korban. וכתיב uchsiv and another verse says מיום השמיני והלאה
ירצה. miyom hashemini vahala yeratze.
Only on the beginning of the day of the eighth is it
fit. So what's the story the night of the eighth, the night
leading into the eighth? It's after seven days with its mother but
it's not yet the eighth day. So הא כיצד? ha keitzad? How
does this work? לילה לקדושה, laila lekeddusha, the night before you can
sanctify it. It's not like you if you sanctify it on day
seven, day six, or whatever, that's נדחה. nidcha. You sanctified an animal
that is פסול pasul to be brought as a קרבן. korban. You
got it? If you sanctified it when it's five days old. Okay,
when you sanctify it when it's the night of the eighth, because
it's eight days old, it's enough able to be sanctified as a
קרבן korban even though it will not yet have had an opportunity
to be brought until the morning, okay, because you don't bring קרבנות
korbanos at night. לילה לקדושה יום להרצאה. laila lekeddusha yom lehertza.
The day is when it could actually be brought as a קרבן.
korban. So the point is when we want to discuss this question:
is this considered נדחה, nidcha, pushed away, can the קדושה keddusha work,
is it the time of the קרבן? korban? We measure those times
in whole day units. Okay. So therefore, and it's actually very consistent,
the same way בערב פסח be'erev pesach says it's פסול pasul here
because it's זמנו zmano because the זמן zman is coming later in
the day, we're also saying that when it's sanctified here the night
before, or sanctified earlier and passed through the night before the day,
it is not entering a time when it can't be brought. We
measure time in whole day units. Okay. And so... Since later today
it can be brought, right, whether it's the morning, whether it's the
night before, later today it can be brought, it's considered the זמן,
zman, and therefore you can sanctify it and it remains כשר. kasher.
OK.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רבי זירא
לרבי אבא, Amar lei Rabbi Zeira le-Rabbi Abba, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
said to רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, לימא קסבר רבי יוחנן בעלי חיים
נדחין? leima kasvar Rabbi Yochanan baalei chayim nidchin? Now the very fact
that we were bothered with this question, oh, it passes through this
time and it has to be pushed off and we said no,
it'll be brought later in the day, it's not considered that it's
לא זמנו. lo zmano. But this is a live animal. And there's
a debate whether we say this idea of being pushed off and
stigmatized applies to live animals or only to like sacrifice once it's
been slaughtered. And you understand it, like the sense that it's alive
has this implication of like this dynamism that something is not totally
static and its identity cannot be like totally labeled and categorized, right?
It's very powerful, like the whole idea of תשובה teshuva or whatever.
You know, we're not like, you know, we're a dynamic living thing,
maybe cannot be like just stigmatized and pushed away. So that's his
idea that, so that's that debate. Do you say live animals are
נדחין nidchin or does it only work this idea of דחוי, dichui,
it's pushed away, stigmatized, can never be כשר kasher again as a
קרבן korban only if it's שחט? shechted? So since this whole discussion
was the live animal that you're sanctifying and we had to figure
it out, well, it's the same day so it's not דחוי, dichui,
that makes it sound like fundamentally live animals can be נדחה. nidcha.
OK. So this makes it sound לימא קסבר רבי יוחנן בעלי חיים
נדחין, leima kasvar Rabbi Yochanan baalei chayim nidchin, live animals can be
pushed away.
Like how you can't do תשובה teshuva after, I mean in that
context, after you're dead.
Right. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, אין,
in, yes, that's correct, דאמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and I'll
give you another example where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan talks about דחוי
dichui by live animals. בהמה של שני שותפים הקדיש חציה וחזר ולקח
חציה והקדישה. Behema shel shenei shutafim hikdish chatziya ve-chazar ve-lakach chatziya ve-hikdisha.
So here David and I own this little sheep, well let's say
Mary and I, Mary's little lamb, owned a little lamb, OK, and
in partnership. I sanctify my half. So it doesn't sanctify the whole
animal because it can't define the half that's hers. If it was
all mine and I sanctified half, the קדושה kedusha would spread throughout.
But it's half hers. So my sanctity can't redefine her half, OK?
And then, so then I go and I buy Mary's half off
of her. And then I sanctify the second half. So now it's
all sanctified as an עולה. olah. But the first time it was
sanctified it had half sanctity of an עולה, olah, it couldn't be
brought because it was only half sanctified.
וחזר ולקח חציה והקדישה, ve-chazar ve-lakach chatziya ve-hikdisha, and then I sanctify
the second half. קדושה ואינה קריבה. Kedusha ve-eina kreiva. It's holy, but
it can't be brought. Why can't it be brought? That even though
now it has full sanctity, when it had there was a time
when it had sanctity that couldn't be brought, when it was only
half sanctified. So that's נדחה. nidcha. Even though now it's in its
full state, OK, because of its previous state of sanctified but not
able to be brought, it remains pushed away. ועושה תמורה Ve-oseh tmura
and by the way since I now fully own it, it's not
a partnership, I can make a תמורה, tmura, meaning I'm not allowed
to, but if I do it's effective. ותמורתה כיוצא בה U-tmurata k'yo-tzei
bah and if I make a תמורה, tmura, the other תמורה tmura
has the same status, that it's sanctified but can't be brought. Anyway.
ושמע מינה תלת. Ve-shma mina tlat. We see from this three things.
שמע מינה בעלי חיים נדחין Shma mina baalei chayim nidchin that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan assumes even a live animal can be pushed off
and remains stigmatized and not brought again. ושמע מינה דחוי מעיקרא הוי
דחוי, Ve-shma mina dichui mei-ikara havei dichui, even if it was pushed
off from the beginning, meaning as I said, it's worse when it
was fit and then became unfit, that's more of a stigma. Some
people say that if it was never fit then it doesn't really
get remain pushed off and it can become fit. OK, but he
doesn't say that. Even though it was never fit as a קרבן,
korban, it was דחוי מעיקרא dichui mei-ikara from the beginning, it remains
stigmatized. ושמע מינה Ve-shma mina and the third one is יש דחוי
בדמים. yesh dichui be-damim. Even though the sanctity was not a sanctity
of bringing it as a מזבח mizbeach to the altar, I only
sanctified half of it and it wasn't initially fit to be brought
as a קרבן, korban, nevertheless it was only a קדושת דמים kedushat
damim of the value, it was never fully fit, that also makes
it pushed off. Now there's a whole big תוספות Tosafot that understands
wait, what's the difference between דחוי בדמים dichui be-damim and דחוי מעיקרא?
dichui mei-ikara? דחוי מעיקרא Dichui mei-ikara means it was never fit so
it never fully had sanctity for the altar, so it only had
sanctity for its value. So there's a whole question what this third
דחוי בדמים dichui be-damim means. We're not going to sort of spend
too much time on it. Partly it might have to do with
the fact that the גמרא Gemara likes threes. Like the גמרא Gemara
says never says שמע מינה תרתי. shma mina tartei. The גמרא Gemara
only has שמע מינה תלת. shma mina tlat. It never says שמע
מינה ארבע, shma mina arba, never says שמע מינה תרתי. shma mina
tartei. There's always three lessons to be learned. It's a good speaker
skill, right? There are three points I want to make. Figure out
what the third one is or cut your four down to three.
OK, anyway so the third one here is a little bit unclear
what דחוי בדמים dichui be-damim means, how is that different than דחוי
מעיקרא. dichui mei-ikara. Anyway.
Does it suggest that it might be the threes? What? Is that
תוספות? Tosafot?
No, that's not תוספות. Tosafot. That's my point. OK. אמר הוא. Amar
hu. תוספות Tosafot comes up with other explanations of what דחוי בדמים
dichui be-damim means.
We got three lists for a synthesis.
Right. OK. Yeah, right. But it's also just a memory aid. We
think that way anyway. אמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Ulla amar
Rabbi Yochanan. אכל חלב. Achal chelev. Now we're going to get to
other interesting cases of דחוי. dichui. And Michal gave me a mandate.
to get to the משנה, Mishnah, so let's see if we can
do it. אמר עולא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan,
אכל חלב והפריש קרבן והמיר דת. achal cheilev vehifrish korban ve-hemir dat.
This is fun. Okay, this guy ראובן, Reuven, he ate חלב cheilev
and then he separated out his קרבן korban for חלב. cheilev. He
did it בשוגג, be-shogeg, and then he says, "That's it, I'm giving
up this religion," or "I'm certainly now, I'm just going to commit
myself to eating חלב cheilev the rest of my life." Okay, and
he now as a מומר, mumar, as somebody who is a rebel,
a rejecter, either of all of the תורה Torah or of this
מצוה mitzvah or whatever. Anyway, he no longer is fit for bringing
a קרבן korban בגברא, be-gavra, like his personal status is one that
he can't bring a קרבן korban for this חטא, chet, for this
sin if he has completely rejected it at this stage. וחזר בו,
Ve-chazar bo, and then he did תשובה, teshuvah, says, "Nah, whatever, I
will start keeping הלכה." halakhah. Okay, הואיל ונדחה ידחה. Hoil ve-nidcha yidache.
Since during that state of his rejection, the קרבן korban was pushed
away, it was considered
זבח רשעים zevach risha'im is the phrase the גמרא Gemara uses, it's
an unfit קרבן, korban, he's unfit to bring it, then it remains
invalid and now he has to bring- separate a new קרבן, korban,
that one became invalid. Okay.
Judaism doesn't recognize apostasy?
Well, that- well, it has a category of מומר, mumar, but that's
true. Yeah, not in a permanent sense, not in a permanent sense.
איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, אמר רבי ירמיה אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי
יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yirmiyah amar Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Yochanan, אכל חלב
והפריש קרבן ונשתטה. achal cheilev vehifrish korban ve-nishtateh. Here's similar, not that
he became a רשע, rasha, a מומר, mumar, but he actually had
a state of, like, a mental illness. Okay, that's what נשתטה nishtateh
means, he had a state of, like, you know, he was like,
maybe he was dealing with paranoia or something, so he entered into
a state of mental- of being mentally unstable, mental illness. וחזר ונשתפה,
Ve-chazar ve-nishtafa, and then things calmed down for him, okay, and now
he's thinking clearly. הואיל ונדחה ידחה. Hoil ve-nidcha yidache. Since- since he
can't bring it when he's not in his right mind, so he
was in a stage where it could not be brought, so it
remains pushed off and now he has to separate a new קרבן.
korban. Okay, וצריכא, U-tzricha, you need to tell me both cases. Okay,
by the way, both- notice that both of them are cases of
בעלי חיים, ba'alei chayim, although they're cases of נראה ונדחה, nireh ve-nidcha,
right, it was fit and then it got pushed away? Anyway, you
need to tell me both cases. דאי אשמעינן קמייתא, De-i ashmi'inan kammaita,
if you told me the case of the מומר, mumar, משום דהוא
דחי נפשיה בידיים, mishum de-hu dachi nafshei be-yadayim, that's more of a
rejection, he himself willingly pushed himself out of that category. אבל הכא
דממילא אידחי, Aval hacha de-mimmela idchi, but now where it just happened,
like, out of his control, right, he just became, you know, he
got this state, this fugue or whatever, this state of mental illness,
כי ישן דמי, ki yashen dami, maybe it's like he's sleeping. It's
not like he's rejecting it. He's in a state and maybe we
hope that the state will naturally undo itself and so on. Anyway,
it's not the same degree of rejection, so I might think that
that would be כשר, kasher, it's not completely נדחה. nidcha. ואי אשמעינן
הכא, Ve-i ashmi'inan hacha, if you told me the state of שוטה,
shoteh, משום דאין בידו לחזור, mishum de-ein be-yado lachazor, the flip side
of that it happened to him was that he can't undo it
by himself. Okay, and therefore- it's like a coma? Right, well, I'm
going to- I'll mention coma in a minute. Yeah, but that's a
good analogy. It's not like sleeping, it's like a coma. Maybe you'll
wake up, maybe you won't, but it's not necessarily a natural cycle.
Okay.
משום דאין בידו לחזור. Mishum de-ein be-yado lachazor. Now, one wonders what
if it is a natural cycle, what if somebody actually does enter
in and out of these states, they never stay in those states
permanently? You do expect it to pass, but it's still not in
his control. And since it's not in his control, even though you
expect it to pass, there's more of a sense of it's fully
pushed off. He cannot bring it back out of his will. Okay,
and- so therefore, אבל הכא דיש בידו לחזור, aval hacha de-yesh be-yado
lachazor, here where he became a מומר mumar that he can willingly,
you know, choose to do תשובה, teshuvah, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe
it's not considered totally pushed off. Any time he wants, he can
decide to do תשובה. teshuvah. צריכא, Tzricha, so you have to tell
me that both of those are considered to be pushed off. And
by the way, it's an interesting issue that came up once,
you know, about- somebody asked me, like, that there was a family
that was, you know, they had somebody in the hospital and he
was- he was brain dead, but the family was not going by
the halakhic definition of- by brain death as the halakhic definition of
death, and they were still praying for a רפואה refuah and so
on. Anyway, and they were דאווענינג, davening, you know, and they- they
would have like a מנין, minyan, מנחה mincha מנין minyan like in
the room. And there was once that they only had nine men
in the room and this person, so they wanted to count him
for a מנין minyan because they were still considering him to be
alive. You know, but I said- so anyway, so- so somebody asked
me about this, I said no, look, even if you consider him
alive, it's sort of like the point made, it's like he's in
a coma. It's one thing, there's a debate if somebody is sleeping,
can he be counted as a מנין? minyan? But that's exactly like
this, 'cause sleep, the natural cycle is, is that he'll, like, wake
up, okay, but somebody who's in a coma, that there's no natural
cycle that they'll wake up, right, is certainly, you know, not considered
to be enough present to count in a מנין. minyan. So קל
וחומר kal va-chomer this case. But anyway. Is a
sleeping person a מנין minyan person? Sleeping person is a debate, I
don't know- I mean, I don't know למעשה le-ma'aseh how the פוסקים
poskim conclude about that.
But a person in a מנין minyan has to participate.
No, not necessarily. Let's say the janitor. All right, not necessarily. Sometimes
they do that, they get the guy who's sweeping in the back
or whatever and they just count him. Anyway, whatever, I don't want
to have- don't want to go into that discussion. Okay, now, בעי
רבי ירמיה, Ba'ei Rabbi Yirmiyah, did I skip a line? Yeah. בעא
רבי ירמיה. Ba'ei Rabi Yirmiya. Rabi Yirmiya asked. Did I skip something?
Yeah. בעא רבי ירמיה אכל חלב והפריש קרבן. Ba'ei Rabi Yirmiya achal
chelev vehifrish korban. Ah, just to remind you that we just learned
הוריות. Horayos. You ate חלב chelev and then you separated a קרבן
korban והורו בית דין שחלב מותר. vehoru Beis Din shechelev mutar. Now
בית דין Beis Din פסקו paskened actually what you just did, they
said it's actually technically מותר. mutar. They're פסקו paskening it incorrectly. But
now you're in a time where if somebody were to do the
sin that you did yesterday, they would be told it was not
a sin and they wouldn't have to bring a קרבן. korban. Okay,
וחזרו בהן. vechazru bahen. And then בית דין Beis Din said oh
whoops, we made a mistake. Okay, now מהו? mahu? Do we say
since you passed through a time where what the act that you
did was not considered a sin and not obligated in a קרבן,
korban, does that mean that the קרבן korban is pushed off? Because
at that time
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash wouldn't have accepted your קרבן. korban. They
would have said this what you did wasn't a sin. What do
we say? מי הוי דיחוי או לא, הוי דיחוי? Mi havei dichuy
o lo, havei dichuy? Is it pushed off or not? אמר ליה
ההוא סבא, Amrei lei hahu saba, certain elder said, כי פתח רבי
יוחנן בדיחוים, Ki pasach Rabi Yochanan bedichuyim, when רבי יוחנן, Rabi Yochanan,
and clearly רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan had a lot to say about
דיחוי, dichuy, when רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan would start learning the topic
of דיחוי, dichuy, מה פתח, Mah pasach, that would be his opening
case, would be the case of הוריות Horayos and בית דין's Beis
Din פסק. psak. That would be his perfect example of דיחוי. dichuy.
Why is it a perfect example of דיחוי? dichuy? You ask me,
if בית דין Beis Din is making a mistake then it turns
out retroactively that the whole thing was an error, right? And you
know, and like it was just a mistake. It all it always
was that I had done a sin. בית דין Beis Din just
was a period where they were telling people the wrong thing. But
surprisingly the גמרא Gemara says no, at that time that actually was
a period of time where הלכתית halachically at least it was understood
to be okay. Why? מאי טעמא התם גברא אידחי קרבן לא אידחי.
Mai ta'ama hasam gavra idchi korban lo idchi. In the other cases
where the guy becomes a שוטה shoteh or a מומה, muma, he
personally is not fit to bring a קרבן, korban, but there's nothing
about the idea that the sin that he did is not a
sin and is not a type of a sin that's obligated in
a קרבן. korban. הכא קרבן נמי אידחי. Hacha korban nami idchi. Here
you pass through a time where there was no meaning for a
קרבן korban for this sin, because this thing wasn't considered to be
a sin. So since therefore the the idea of a קרבן korban
for what you did was meaningless during this time, that's a clear
stigma on the קרבן. korban. As opposed to the other cases, you
have a קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, you're right now in a certain
state where you can't bring it, but there's nothing wrong about the
idea of this as a קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. So he actually
felt that that case was the more obvious case of דיחוי. dichuy.
I don't know, you ask me, it's the less obvious, but okay.
Let's keep on going. אמר שמעון בן עזאי מקובלני מפי שבעים ושנים
זקנים, Amar Shimon ben Azai mikublani mipi shivim ushnayim zekeinim, I have
a tradition from seventy-two elders. Now our גירסא girsa is שבעים ושנים
זקן, shivim ushnayim zakein, seventy-two elder in the singular. So למה לי
למיתני שבעים ושנים זקן, lama li limisnei shivim ushnayim zakein, why does
it say זקן zakein in the singular? דכולא בחדא שיטתא הוו קיימי,
Dekula bechada shitasa hava kaimei, they were all like of a unanimous
position, they were all there present at the same time, they all
spoke כאיש אחד בלב אחד, ke'ish echad belev echad, that's his version.
Okay, that's ארבעים יום וארבעים לילה. arba'im yom ve'arba'im layla.
Yeah,
but שנים shenayim requires you to
say if it's a round
number,
oh yeah, yeah, שנים shenayim requires you to say זקנים. zekeinim. והוסיף
בן עזאי אלא העולה. Vehosif ben Azai ela ha'olah. Now what implicitly
בן עזאי ben Azai is adding to his list is the עולה.
olah. The גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna,
מאי טעמא דבן עזאי, Mai ta'ama deBen Azai, what does בן עזאי
ben Azai say an עולה olah שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is פסול?
pasul? Because it says, well he really says it because he had
his tradition, but anyway,
עולה הוא אשי ריח ניחוח לה'. olah hu ishei rei'ach nicho'ach l'Hashem.
הוא לשמה כשרה שלא לשמה פסולה. Hu lishmah kesheira shelo lishmah pesulah.
Is it עולה היא? olah hi? I guess it's עולה היא. olah
hi. אשי ריח ניחוח לה'. ishei rei'ach nicho'ach l'Hashem. היא לשמה כשרה
שלא לשמה פסולה. Hi lishmah kesheira shelo lishmah pesulah. So it only
only done the right way, only when it's לשמה lishmah it's עולה
הוא. olah hu. עולה הוא. olah hu.
קרבן korban is masculine or feminine?
עולה olah is feminine.
I thought yesterday חטאת chatas was.
Right. Okay, right. עולה הוא olah hu אשי ריח ניחוח לה'. ishei
rei'ach nicho'ach l'Hashem. Fine, that's what the פסוק pasuk says. Fine, all
right. Moving on. לשמה כשרה שלא לשמה פסולה. lishmah kesheira shelo lishmah
pesulah. So the גמרא Gemara says אשם נמי כתיב ביה הוא, Asham
nami ksiv bei hu, by אשם asham it also says הוא hu
like we've been discussing. No, הוא לאחר הקטרת אימורין דכתיב, hu lachar
haktaras emurin dicsiv, that's only after you burn the אימורין emurin so
that can't invalidate the central things that make the קרבן כשר. korban
kasher. האי נמי לאחר הקטרת אימורין דכתיב, Hai nami lachar haktaras emurin
dicsiv, by עולה olah it's also the פסוק pasuk that's referring to
is also after the אימורין emurin are being
burned. תרי הוא כתיבי, Trei hu kesivei, it says הוא hu twice.
רש"י Rashi lists where these where these appear. So the second time
is to tell you that even during the central עבודה avodah of
the דם, dam, it has to be done דוקא לשמה davka lishmah
and שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is invalid. אשם נמי תרי הוא כתיבי,
Asham nami trei hu kesivei, by אשם asham it also says הוא
hu twice. Fine, says the גמרא, Gemara, it's not based on the
פסוקים. psukim. אלא בן עזאי בקל וחומר מייתי לה. Ela ben Azai
bekal vachomer maisei lah. He learns it out of a logic, out
of a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה חטאת שאינה כליל שחטה שלא
לשמה פסולה, Umah chatas she'eina kalil shachatah shelo lishmah pesulah, a חטאת
chatas that you don't burn totally, so it's not the holiest thing,
we keep some of it, it doesn't all go to God, and
that שלא לשמה shelo lishmah is פסולה. pesulah. עולה שהיא כליל לא
כל שכן? olah shehi kalil lo kol shekein? So an עולה olah
which is the holiest, it's all burnt, it all goes to God,
certainly שלא לשמה shelo lishmah should be פסול. pasul. No, you could
challenge the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה לחטאת שכן מכפרת, Mah lechatas
sheken mechaperes, a חטאת chatas atones and that therefore it has this
higher requirement. פסח יוכיח. Pesach yochiach. No, פסח Pesach will prove that
atoning is not central. And that's also פסול שלא לשמה. pasul shelo
lishmah. מה לפסח שכן זמנו קבוע, Mah lepesach sheken zemano kavua, for
פסח Pesach has a fixed time, that's what makes it. higher requirement.
No, חטאת תוכיח *Chatat tochiach*. חטאת *Chatat* will prove that that's not
central. וחזר הדין *vechazar hadin*. It goes back and forth. לא ראי
זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה *lo re'i ze kire'i
ze velo re'i ze kire'i ze*. הצד השווה שבהן *hatzad hashaveh shebahen*,
the common denominator, שכן קדשים ושחטן שלא לשמן פסול *shechein kodashim veshachtan
shelo lishman pasul*. They're קדשים *kodashim* and שחטן שלא לשמן פסול *shachtan
shelo lishman pasul*, אף אני אביא עולה *af ani avi olah*, I'll
bring an עולה *olah* שקדשים ושחטה שלא לשמה פסול *shekodashim veshachtah shelo
lishmah pasul*. The problem with that is once you make that common
denominator, all קרבנות *korbanot* should be פסול שלא לשמן *pasul shelo lishman*.
So it seems to be that there's an additional element that you
still want to limit it to עולה *olah* because עולה *olah* has
the highest sanctity. So because עולה *olah* has the highest sanctity, it
should be invalid שלא לשמה *shelo lishmah*, and don't start telling me
about other concerns, considerations like מכפרת *mechaperet*, זמנו קבוע *zmano kavua*, those
are not critical as we see by the צד השווה *tzad hashaveh*.
And therefore because the עולה *olah* has the highest sanctity, it should
also be invalid שלא לשמה *shelo lishmah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
one minute, מה להצד השווה שבהן שכן יש בהן צד כרת *ma
lehatzad hashaveh shebahen shechein yesh bahen tzad karet*? But one minute, פסח
*Pesach* and a חטאת *Chatat* both have a כרת *karet* aspect to
them. If you don't bring a פסח *Pesach* you get כרת *karet*,
a חטאת *Chatat* atones for כרת *karet*. So therefore you should not
be able to expand that to an עולה *olah*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says בן עזאי צד כרת לא פרך *Ben Azzai tzad karet
lo parech*. He's not impressed with that. Okay, they're not the same
thing, one is to atone for כרת *karet*, one is if you
don't do it you get כרת *karet*, or you could also say
that a חטאת *Chatat*, there's a חטאת *Chatat* that's not based on
a כרת *karet*, עולה ויורד *olah veyored*. He doesn't see that as
a reason to say you can't learn from פסח *Pesach* and חטאת
*Chatat*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says if that's true, אשם נמי ליתי
*asham nami leisei*? So then let's learn אשם *asham*, let's say since
an אשם *asham* is like a חטאת *Chatat* and so on and
learn it from this מה הצד *ma hatzad*, why are you limiting
yourself to an עולה *olah*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, אשם
פרך *asham parech*, no, he has another reason to exclude אשם *asham*.
מה להצד השווה שבהן שכן ישנן בציבור כביחיד *ma lehatzad hashaveh shebahen
shechein yeshnan betzibbur keveyachid*. A חטאת *Chatat* and a פסח *Pesach* are
brought בציבור *betzibbur*. חטאת *Chatat* like, you know, like הוריות *Horayos* would
be a case or on ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* or whatever, and
a פסח *Pesach* even though it's an individual קרבן *korban* it's brought
everybody together, okay, whereas an אשם *asham* you don't have an אשם
*asham* of a ציבור *tzibbur*. Okay, so he wants to limit it
to things that have a ציבור *tzibbur* component. So פסח *Pesach* yes,
פסח *Pesach* and חטאת *Chatat* yes, and עולה *olah* yes, but not
an אשם *asham*. That's how he wants to make his argument. ואיבעית
אימא *ve'iba'is eima* and if you want I could tell you, צד
כרת נמי פרך *tzad karet nami parech*. You're right, it's not based
on a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, you could, פסח *Pesach* and a
חטאת *Chatat* are about כרת *karet* or connected to כרת *karet*, you
can't apply it to other things. So then how does he know
that an עולה שלא לשמה *olah shelo lishmah* is פסול *pasul*? ובן
עזאי גמרא גמיר לה *uven Azzai gemara gmir lah*. He just had
a tradition. He doesn't learn it from a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*,
he doesn't learn it from a פסוק *pasuk*, that's what he's saying.
He says I have a tradition. So the גמרא *Gemara* says והא
דקאמר רב הונא קל וחומר *veha dekamar Rav Huna kal vachomer*? So
why did רב הונא *Rav Huna* throw out a קל וחומר *kal
vachomer* if it's based on a tradition? לחדודי לתלמידיה *lechadudei letalmidiah*. He
wanted to sharpen the students. He wanted to see like, you know,
can they work out the קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, can they raise
the right challenges, can they figure out why it will work or
won't work, it's a little like exercise at home for the reader.
See if you can make this work for a קל וחומר *kal
vachomer* and see what ways you could challenge the קל וחומר *kal
vachomer*, okay, and come back tomorrow. So we will end with that
and come back tomorrow where מיכה *Micha* will pick us up on
the next דף
*daf*.